CHAPTER VII.
MR.
BENNET’S property consisted almost entirely in an estate of two thousand a year, which,
unfortunately for his daughters, was entailed, in default of heirs male, on a distant relation;
and their mother’s fortune, though ample for her situation in life, could but ill supply
the deficiency of his.
Her father had been an attorney in Meryton, and had left her four thousand pounds.
She had a sister married to a Mr. Philips, who had been a clerk to their father and succeeded
him in the business, and a brother settled in London in a respectable line of trade.
The village of Longbourn was only one mile from Meryton; a most convenient distance for
the young ladies, who were usually tempted thither three or four times a week, to pay
their duty to their aunt, and to a milliner’s shop just over the way.
The two youngest of the family, Catherine and Lydia, were particularly frequent in these
attentions: their minds were more vacant than their sisters’, and when nothing better
offered, a walk to Meryton was necessary to amuse their morning hours and furnish conversation
for the evening; and, however bare of news the country in general might be, they always
contrived to learn some from their aunt.
At present, indeed, they were well supplied both with news and happiness by the recent
arrival of a militia regiment in the neighbourhood; it was to remain the whole winter, and Meryton
was the head-quarters.
Their visits to Mrs. Philips were now productive of the most interesting intelligence.
Every day added something to their knowledge of the officers’ names and connections.
Their lodgings were not long a secret, and at length they began to know the officers
themselves.
Mr. Philips visited them all, and this opened to his nieces a source of felicity unknown
before.
They could talk of nothing but officers; and Mr. Bingley’s large fortune, the mention
of which gave animation to their mother, was worthless in their eyes when opposed to the
regimentals of an ensign.
After listening one morning to their effusions on this subject, Mr. Bennet coolly observed,—
“From all that I can collect by your manner of talking, you must be two of the silliest
girls in the country.
I have suspected it some time, but I am now convinced.”
Catherine was disconcerted, and made no answer; but Lydia, with perfect indifference, continued
to express her admiration of Captain Carter, and her hope of seeing him in the course of
the day, as he was going the next morning to London.
“I am astonished, my dear,” said Mrs. Bennet, “that you should be so ready to
think your own children silly.
If I wished to think slightingly of anybody’s children, it should not be of my own, however.”
“If my children are silly, I must hope to be always sensible of it.”
“Yes; but as it happens, they are all of them very clever.”
“This is the only point, I flatter myself, on which we do not agree.
I had hoped that our sentiments coincided in every particular, but I must so far differ
from you as to think our two youngest daughters uncommonly foolish.”
“My dear Mr. Bennet, you must not expect such girls to have the sense of their father
and mother.
When they get to our age, I dare say they will not think about officers any more than
we do.
I remember the time when I liked a red coat myself very well—and, indeed, so I do still
at my heart; and if a smart young colonel, with five or six thousand a year, should want
one of my girls, I shall not say nay to him; and I thought Colonel Forster looked very
becoming the other night at Sir William’s in his regimentals.”
“Mamma,” cried Lydia, “my aunt says that Colonel Forster and Captain Carter do
not go so often to Miss Watson’s as they did when they first came; she sees them now
very often standing in Clarke’s library.”
Mrs. Bennet was prevented replying by the entrance of the footman with a note for Miss
Bennet; it came from Netherfield, and the servant waited for an answer.
Mrs. Bennet’s eyes sparkled with pleasure, and she was eagerly calling out, while her
daughter read,— “Well, Jane, who is it from?
What is it about?
What does he say?
Well, Jane, make haste and tell us; make haste, my love.”
“It is from Miss Bingley,” said Jane, and then read it aloud.
“My dear friend, “If you are not so compassionate as to dine
to-day with Louisa and me, we shall be in danger of hating each other for the rest of
our lives; for a whole day’s tête-à-tête between two women can never end without a
quarrel.
Come as soon as you can on the receipt of this.
My brother and the gentlemen are to dine with the officers.
Yours ever, “Caroline Bingley.”
“With the officers!”
cried Lydia: “I wonder my aunt did not tell us of that.”
“Dining out,” said Mrs. Bennet; “that is very unlucky.”
“Can I have the carriage?” said Jane.
“No, my dear, you had better go on horseback, because it seems likely to rain; and then
you must stay all night.”
“That would be a good scheme,” said Elizabeth, “if you were sure that they would not offer
to send her home.”
“Oh, but the gentlemen will have Mr. Bingley’s chaise to go to Meryton; and the Hursts have
no horses to theirs.”
“I had much rather go in the coach.”
“But, my dear, your father cannot spare the horses, I am sure.
They are wanted in the farm, Mr. Bennet, are not they?”
Cheerful prognostics “They are wanted in the farm much oftener
than I can get them.”
“But if you have got them to-day,” said Elizabeth, “my mother’s purpose will be
answered.”
She did at last extort from her father an acknowledgment that the horses were engaged;
Jane was therefore obliged to go on horseback, and her mother attended her to the door with
many cheerful prognostics of a bad day.
Her hopes were answered; Jane had not been gone long before it rained hard.
Her sisters were uneasy for her, but her mother was delighted.
The rain continued the whole evening without intermission; Jane certainly could not come
back.
“This was a lucky idea of mine, indeed!” said Mrs. Bennet, more than once, as if the
credit of making it rain were all her own.
Till the next morning, however, she was not aware of all the felicity of her contrivance.
Breakfast was scarcely over when a servant from Netherfield brought the following note
for Elizabeth:— “My dearest Lizzie,
“I find myself very unwell this morning, which, I suppose, is to be imputed to my getting
wet through yesterday.
My kind friends will not hear of my returning home till I am better.
They insist also on my seeing Mr. Jones—therefore do not be alarmed if you should hear of his
having been to me—and, excepting a sore throat and a headache, there is not much the
matter with me.
“Yours, etc.”
“Well, my dear,” said Mr. Bennet, when Elizabeth had read the note aloud, “if your
daughter should have a dangerous fit of illness—if she should die—it would be a comfort to
know that it was all in pursuit of Mr. Bingley, and under your orders.”
“Oh, I am not at all afraid of her dying.
People do not die of little trifling colds.
She will be taken good care of.
As long as she stays there, it is all very well.
I would go and see her if I could have the carriage.”
Elizabeth, feeling really anxious, determined to go to her, though the carriage was not
to be had: and as she was no horsewoman, walking was her only alternative.
She declared her resolution.
“How can you be so silly,” cried her mother, “as to think of such a thing, in all this
dirt!
You will not be fit to be seen when you get there.”
“I shall be very fit to see Jane—which is all I want.”
“Is this a hint to me, Lizzy,” said her father, “to send for the horses?”
“No, indeed.
I do not wish to avoid the walk.
The distance is nothing, when one has a motive; only three miles.
I shall be back by dinner.”
“I admire the activity of your benevolence,” observed Mary, “but every impulse of feeling
should be guided by reason; and, in my opinion, exertion should always be in proportion to
what is required.”
“We will go as far as Meryton with you,” said Catherine and Lydia.
Elizabeth accepted their company, and the three young ladies set off together.
“If we make haste,” said Lydia, as they walked along, “perhaps we may see something
of Captain Carter, before he goes.”
In Meryton they parted: the two youngest repaired to the lodgings of one of the officers’
wives, and Elizabeth continued her walk alone, crossing field after field at a quick pace,
jumping over stiles and springing over puddles, with impatient activity, and finding herself
at last within view of the house, with weary ancles, dirty stockings, and a face glowing
with the warmth of exercise.
She was shown into the breakfast parlour, where all but Jane were assembled, and where
her appearance created a great deal of surprise.
That she should have walked three miles so early in the day in such dirty weather, and
by herself, was almost incredible to Mrs. Hurst and Miss Bingley; and Elizabeth was
convinced that they held her in contempt for it.
She was received, however, very politely by them; and in their brother’s manners there
was something better than politeness—there was good-humour and kindness.
Mr. Darcy said very little, and Mr. Hurst nothing at all.
The former was divided between admiration of the brilliancy which exercise had given
to her complexion and doubt as to the occasion’s justifying her coming so far alone.
The latter was thinking only of his breakfast.
Her inquiries after her sister were not very favourably answered.
Miss Bennet had slept ill, and though up, was very feverish, and not well enough to
leave her room.
Elizabeth was glad to be taken to her immediately; and Jane, who had only been withheld by the
fear of giving alarm or inconvenience, from expressing in her note how much she longed
for such a visit, was delighted at her entrance.
She was not equal, however, to much conversation; and when Miss Bingley left them together,
could attempt little beside expressions of gratitude for the extraordinary kindness she
was treated with.
Elizabeth silently attended her.
“The Apothecary came” When breakfast was over, they were joined
by the sisters; and Elizabeth began to like them herself, when she saw how much affection
and solicitude they showed for Jane.
The apothecary came; and having examined his patient, said, as might be supposed, that
she had caught a violent cold, and that they must endeavour to get the better of it; advised
her to return to bed, and promised her some draughts.
The advice was followed readily, for the feverish symptoms increased, and her head ached acutely.
Elizabeth did not quit her room for a moment, nor were the other ladies often absent; the
gentlemen being out, they had in fact nothing to do elsewhere.
When the clock struck three, Elizabeth felt that she must go, and very unwillingly said
so.
Miss Bingley offered her the carriage, and she only wanted a little pressing to accept
it, when Jane testified such concern at parting with her that Miss Bingley was obliged to
convert the offer of the chaise into an invitation to remain at Netherfield for the present.
Elizabeth most thankfully consented, and a servant was despatched to Longbourn, to acquaint
the family with her stay, and bring back a supply of clothes.
Covering a screen.
CHAPTER VIII.
AT five o’clock the two ladies retired to dress, and at half-past six Elizabeth was
summoned to dinner.
To the civil inquiries which then poured in, and amongst which she had the pleasure of
distinguishing the much superior solicitude of Mr. Bingley, she could not make a very
favourable answer.
Jane was by no means better.
The sisters, on hearing this, repeated three or four times how much they were grieved,
how shocking it was to have a bad cold, and how excessively they disliked being ill themselves;
and then thought no more of the matter: and their indifference towards Jane, when not
immediately before them, restored Elizabeth to the enjoyment of all her original dislike.
Their brother, indeed, was the only one of the party whom she could regard with any complacency.
His anxiety for Jane was evident, and his attentions to herself most pleasing; and they
prevented her feeling herself so much an intruder as she believed she was considered by the
others.
She had very little notice from any but him.
Miss Bingley was engrossed by Mr. Darcy, her sister scarcely less so; and as for Mr. Hurst,
by whom Elizabeth sat, he was an indolent man, who lived only to eat, drink, and play
at cards, who, when he found her prefer a plain dish to a ragout, had nothing to say
to her.
When dinner was over, she returned directly to Jane, and Miss Bingley began abusing her
as soon as she was out of the room.
Her manners were pronounced to be very bad indeed,—a mixture of pride and impertinence:
she had no conversation, no style, no taste, no beauty.
Mrs. Hurst thought the same, and added,— “She has nothing, in short, to recommend
her, but being an excellent walker.
I shall never forget her appearance this morning.
She really looked almost wild.”
“She did indeed, Louisa.
I could hardly keep my countenance.
Very nonsensical to come at all!
Why must she be scampering about the country, because her sister had a cold?
Her hair so untidy, so blowzy!”
“Yes, and her petticoat; I hope you saw her petticoat, six inches deep in mud, I am
absolutely certain, and the gown which had been let down to hide it not doing its office.”
“Your picture may be very exact, Louisa,” said Bingley; “but this was all lost upon
me.
I thought Miss Elizabeth Bennet looked remarkably well when she came into the room this morning.
Her dirty petticoat quite escaped my notice.”
“You observed it, Mr. Darcy, I am sure,” said Miss Bingley; “and I am inclined to
think that you would not wish to see your sister make such an exhibition.”
“Certainly not.”
“To walk three miles, or four miles, or five miles, or whatever it is, above her ancles
in dirt, and alone, quite alone!
what could she mean by it?
It seems to me to show an abominable sort of conceited independence, a most country-town
indifference to decorum.”
“It shows an affection for her sister that is very pleasing,” said Bingley.
“I am afraid, Mr. Darcy,” observed Miss Bingley, in a half whisper, “that this adventure
has rather affected your admiration of her fine eyes.”
“Not at all,” he replied: “they were brightened by the exercise.”
A short pause followed this speech, and Mrs. Hurst began again,—
“I have an excessive regard for Jane Bennet,—she is really a very sweet girl,—and I wish
with all my heart she were well settled.
But with such a father and mother, and such low connections, I am afraid there is no chance
of it.”
“I think I have heard you say that their uncle is an attorney in Meryton?”
“Yes; and they have another, who lives somewhere near Cheapside.”
“That is capital,” added her sister; and they both laughed heartily.
“If they had uncles enough to fill all Cheapside,” cried Bingley, “it would not make them one
jot less agreeable.”
“But it must very materially lessen their chance of marrying men of any consideration
in the world,” replied Darcy.
To this speech Bingley made no answer; but his sisters gave it their hearty assent, and
indulged their mirth for some time at the expense of their dear friend’s vulgar relations.
With a renewal of tenderness, however, they repaired to her room on leaving the dining-parlour,
and sat with her till summoned to coffee.
She was still very poorly, and Elizabeth would not quit her at all, till late in the evening,
when she had the comfort of seeing her asleep, and when it appeared to her rather right than
pleasant that she should go down stairs herself.
On entering the drawing-room, she found the whole party at loo, and was immediately invited
to join them; but suspecting them to be playing high, she declined it, and making her sister
the excuse, said she would amuse herself, for the short time she could stay below, with
a book.
Mr. Hurst looked at her with astonishment.
“Do you prefer reading to cards?” said he; “that is rather singular.”
“Miss Eliza Bennet,” said Miss Bingley, “despises cards.
She is a great reader, and has no pleasure in anything else.”
“I deserve neither such praise nor such censure,” cried Elizabeth; “I am not a
great reader, and I have pleasure in many things.”
“In nursing your sister I am sure you have pleasure,” said Bingley; “and I hope it
will soon be increased by seeing her quite well.”
Elizabeth thanked him from her heart, and then walked towards a table where a few books
were lying.
He immediately offered to fetch her others; all that his library afforded.
“And I wish my collection were larger for your benefit and my own credit; but I am an
idle fellow; and though I have not many, I have more than I ever looked into.”
Elizabeth assured him that she could suit herself perfectly with those in the room.
“I am astonished,” said Miss Bingley, “that my father should have left so small
a collection of books.
What a delightful library you have at Pemberley, Mr. Darcy!”
“It ought to be good,” he replied: “it has been the work of many generations.”
“And then you have added so much to it yourself—you are always buying books.”
“I cannot comprehend the neglect of a family library in such days as these.”
“Neglect!
I am sure you neglect nothing that can add to the beauties of that noble place.
Charles, when you build your house, I wish it may be half as delightful as Pemberley.”
“I wish it may.”
“But I would really advise you to make your purchase in that neighbourhood, and take Pemberley
for a kind of model.
There is not a finer county in England than Derbyshire.”
“With all my heart: I will buy Pemberley itself, if Darcy will sell it.”
“I am talking of possibilities, Charles.”
“Upon my word, Caroline, I should think it more possible to get Pemberley by purchase
than by imitation.”
Elizabeth was so much caught by what passed, as to leave her very little attention for
her book; and, soon laying it wholly aside, she drew near the card-table, and stationed
herself between Mr. Bingley and his eldest sister, to observe the game.
“Is Miss Darcy much grown since the spring?” said Miss Bingley: “will she be as tall
as I am?”
“I think she will.
She is now about Miss Elizabeth Bennet’s height, or rather taller.”
“How I long to see her again!
I never met with anybody who delighted me so much.
Such a countenance, such manners, and so extremely accomplished for her age!
Her performance on the pianoforte is exquisite.”
“It is amazing to me,” said Bingley, “how young ladies can have patience to be so very
accomplished as they all are.”
“All young ladies accomplished!
My dear Charles, what do you mean?”
“Yes, all of them, I think.
They all paint tables, cover screens, and net purses.
I scarcely know any one who cannot do all this; and I am sure I never heard a young
lady spoken of for the first time, without being informed that she was very accomplished.”
“Your list of the common extent of accomplishments,” said Darcy, “has too much truth.
The word is applied to many a woman who deserves it no otherwise than by netting a purse or
covering a screen; but I am very far from agreeing with you in your estimation of ladies
in general.
I cannot boast of knowing more than half-a-dozen in the whole range of my acquaintance that
are really accomplished.”
“Nor I, I am sure,” said Miss Bingley.
“Then,” observed Elizabeth, “you must comprehend a great deal in your idea of an
accomplished woman.”
“Yes; I do comprehend a great deal in it.”
“Oh, certainly,” cried his faithful assistant, “no one can be really esteemed accomplished
who does not greatly surpass what is usually met with.
A woman must have a thorough knowledge of music, singing, drawing, dancing, and the
modern languages, to deserve the word; and, besides all this, she must possess a certain
something in her air and manner of walking, the tone of her voice, her address and expressions,
or the word will be but half deserved.”
“All this she must possess,” added Darcy; “and to all she must yet add something more
substantial in the improvement of her mind by extensive reading.”
“I am no longer surprised at your knowing only six accomplished women.
I rather wonder now at your knowing any.”
“Are you so severe upon your own sex as to doubt the possibility of all this?”
“I never saw such a woman.
I never saw such capacity, and taste, and application, and elegance, as you describe,
united.”
Mrs. Hurst and Miss Bingley both cried out against the injustice of her implied doubt,
and were both protesting that they knew many women who answered this description, when
Mr. Hurst called them to order, with bitter complaints of their inattention to what was
going forward.
As all conversation was thereby at an end, Elizabeth soon afterwards left the room.
“Eliza Bennet,” said Miss Bingley, when the door was closed on her, “is one of those
young ladies who seek to recommend themselves to the other sex by undervaluing their own;
and with many men, I daresay, it succeeds; but, in my opinion, it is a paltry device,
a very mean art.”
“Undoubtedly,” replied Darcy, to whom this remark was chiefly addressed, “there
is meanness in all the arts which ladies sometimes condescend to employ for captivation.
Whatever bears affinity to cunning is despicable.”
Miss Bingley was not so entirely satisfied with this reply as to continue the subject.
Elizabeth joined them again only to say that her sister was worse, and that she could not
leave her.
Bingley urged Mr. Jones’s being sent for immediately; while his sisters, convinced
that no country advice could be of any service, recommended an express to town for one of
the most eminent physicians.
This she would not hear of; but she was not so unwilling to comply with their brother’s
proposal; and it was settled that Mr. Jones should be sent for early in the morning, if
Miss Bennet were not decidedly better.
Bingley was quite uncomfortable; his sisters declared that they were miserable.
They solaced their wretchedness, however, by duets after supper; while he could find
no better relief to his feelings than by giving his housekeeper directions that every possible
attention might be paid to the sick lady and her sister.
Mrs Bennet and her two youngest girls.
CHAPTER IX.
ELIZABETH passed the chief of the night in her sister’s room, and in the morning had
the pleasure of being able to send a tolerable answer to the inquiries which she very early
received from Mr. Bingley by a housemaid, and some time afterwards from the two elegant
ladies who waited on his sisters.
In spite of this amendment, however, she requested to have a note sent to Longbourn, desiring
her mother to visit Jane, and form her own judgment of her situation.
The note was immediately despatched, and its contents as quickly complied with.
Mrs. Bennet, accompanied by her two youngest girls, reached Netherfield soon after the
family breakfast.
Had she found Jane in any apparent danger, Mrs. Bennet would have been very miserable;
but being satisfied on seeing her that her illness was not alarming, she had no wish
of her recovering immediately, as her restoration to health would probably remove her from Netherfield.
She would not listen, therefore, to her daughter’s proposal of being carried home; neither did
the apothecary, who arrived about the same time, think it at all advisable.
After sitting a little while with Jane, on Miss Bingley’s appearance and invitation,
the mother and three daughters all attended her into the breakfast parlour.
Bingley met them with hopes that Mrs. Bennet had not found Miss Bennet worse than she expected.
“Indeed I have, sir,” was her answer.
“She is a great deal too ill to be moved.
Mr. Jones says we must not think of moving her.
We must trespass a little longer on your kindness.”
“Removed!”
cried Bingley.
“It must not be thought of.
My sister, I am sure, will not hear of her removal.”
“You may depend upon it, madam,” said Miss Bingley, with cold civility, “that
Miss Bennet shall receive every possible attention while she remains with us.”
Mrs. Bennet was profuse in her acknowledgments.
“I am sure,” she added, “if it was not for such good friends, I do not know what
would become of her, for she is very ill indeed, and suffers a vast deal, though with the greatest
patience in the world, which is always the way with her, for she has, without exception,
the sweetest temper I ever met with.
I often tell my other girls they are nothing to her.
You have a sweet room here, Mr. Bingley, and a charming prospect over that gravel walk.
I do not know a place in the country that is equal to Netherfield.
You will not think of quitting it in a hurry, I hope, though you have but a short lease.”
“Whatever I do is done in a hurry,” replied he; “and therefore if I should resolve to
quit Netherfield, I should probably be off in five minutes.
At present, however, I consider myself as quite fixed here.”
“That is exactly what I should have supposed of you,” said Elizabeth.
“You begin to comprehend me, do you?”
cried he, turning towards her.
“Oh yes—I understand you perfectly.”
“I wish I might take this for a compliment; but to be so easily seen through, I am afraid,
is pitiful.”
“That is as it happens.
It does not necessarily follow that a deep, intricate character is more or less estimable
than such a one as yours.”
“Lizzy,” cried her mother, “remember where you are, and do not run on in the wild
manner that you are suffered to do at home.”
“I did not know before,” continued Bingley, immediately, “that you were a studier of
character.
It must be an amusing study.”
“Yes; but intricate characters are the most amusing.
They have at least that advantage.”
“The country,” said Darcy, “can in general supply but few subjects for such a study.
In a country neighbourhood you move in a very confined and unvarying society.”
“But people themselves alter so much, that there is something new to be observed in them
for ever.”
“Yes, indeed,” cried Mrs. Bennet, offended by his manner of mentioning a country neighbourhood.
“I assure you there is quite as much of that going on in the country as in town.”
Everybody was surprised; and Darcy, after looking at her for a moment, turned silently
away.
Mrs. Bennet, who fancied she had gained a complete victory over him, continued her triumph,—
“I cannot see that London has any great advantage over the country, for my part, except
the shops and public places.
The country is a vast deal pleasanter, is not it, Mr. Bingley?”
“When I am in the country,” he replied, “I never wish to leave it; and when I am
in town, it is pretty much the same.
They have each their advantages, and I can be equally happy in either.”
“Ay, that is because you have the right disposition.
But that gentleman,” looking at Darcy, “seemed to think the country was nothing at all.”
“Indeed, mamma, you are mistaken,” said Elizabeth, blushing for her mother.
“You quite mistook Mr. Darcy.
He only meant that there was not such a variety of people to be met with in the country as
in town, which you must acknowledge to be true.”
“Certainly, my dear, nobody said there were; but as to not meeting with many people in
this neighbourhood, I believe there are few neighbourhoods larger.
I know we dine with four-and-twenty families.”
Nothing but concern for Elizabeth could enable Bingley to keep his countenance.
His sister was less delicate, and directed her eye towards Mr. Darcy with a very expressive
smile.
Elizabeth, for the sake of saying something that might turn her mother’s thoughts, now
asked her if Charlotte Lucas had been at Longbourn since her coming away.
“Yes, she called yesterday with her father.
What an agreeable man Sir William is, Mr. Bingley—is not he?
so much the man of fashion!
so genteel and so easy!
He has always something to say to everybody.
That is my idea of good breeding; and those persons who fancy themselves very important
and never open their mouths quite mistake the matter.”
“Did Charlotte dine with you?”
“No, she would go home.
I fancy she was wanted about the mince-pies.
For my part, Mr. Bingley, I always keep servants that can do their own work; my daughters are
brought up differently.
But everybody is to judge for themselves, and the Lucases are a very good sort of girls,
I assure you.
It is a pity they are not handsome!
Not that I think Charlotte so very plain; but then she is our particular friend.”
“She seems a very pleasant young woman,” said Bingley.
“Oh dear, yes; but you must own she is very plain.
Lady Lucas herself has often said so, and envied me Jane’s beauty.
I do not like to boast of my own child; but to be sure, Jane—one does not often see
anybody better looking.
It is what everybody says.
I do not trust my own partiality.
When she was only fifteen there was a gentleman at my brother Gardiner’s in town so much
in love with her, that my sister-in-law was sure he would make her an offer before we
came away.
But, however, he did not.
Perhaps he thought her too young.
However, he wrote some verses on her, and very pretty they were.”
“And so ended his affection,” said Elizabeth, impatiently.
“There has been many a one, I fancy, overcome in the same way.
I wonder who first discovered the efficacy of poetry in driving away love!”
“I have been used to consider poetry as the food of love,” said Darcy.
“Of a fine, stout, healthy love it may.
Everything nourishes what is strong already.
But if it be only a slight, thin sort of inclination, I am convinced that one good sonnet will starve
it entirely away.”
Darcy only smiled; and the general pause which ensued made Elizabeth tremble lest her mother
should be exposing herself again.
She longed to speak, but could think of nothing to say; and after a short silence Mrs. Bennet
began repeating her thanks to Mr. Bingley for his kindness to Jane, with an apology
for troubling him also with Lizzy.
Mr. Bingley was unaffectedly civil in his answer, and forced his younger sister to be
civil also, and say what the occasion required.
She performed her part, indeed, without much graciousness, but Mrs. Bennet was satisfied,
and soon afterwards ordered her carriage.
Upon this signal, the youngest of her daughters put herself forward.
The two girls had been whispering to each other during the whole visit; and the result
of it was, that the youngest should tax Mr. Bingley with having promised on his first
coming into the country to give a ball at Netherfield.
Lydia was a stout, well-grown girl of fifteen, with a fine complexion and good-humoured countenance;
a favourite with her mother, whose affection had brought her into public at an early age.
She had high animal spirits, and a sort of natural self-consequence, which the attentions
of the officers, to whom her uncle’s good dinners and her own easy manners recommended
her, had increased into assurance.
She was very equal, therefore, to address Mr. Bingley on the subject of the ball, and
abruptly reminded him of his promise; adding, that it would be the most shameful thing in
the world if he did not keep it.
His answer to this sudden attack was delightful to her mother’s ear.
“I am perfectly ready, I assure you, to keep my engagement; and, when your sister
is recovered, you shall, if you please, name the very day of the ball.
But you would not wish to be dancing while she is ill?”
Lydia declared herself satisfied.
“Oh yes—it would be much better to wait till Jane was well; and by that time, most
likely, Captain Carter would be at Meryton again.
And when you have given your ball,” she added, “I shall insist on their giving one
also.
I shall tell Colonel Forster it will be quite a shame if he does not.”
Mrs. Bennet and her daughters then departed, and Elizabeth returned instantly to Jane,
leaving her own and her relations’ behaviour to the remarks of the two ladies and Mr. Darcy;
the latter of whom, however, could not be prevailed on to join in their censure of her,
in spite of all Miss Bingley’s witticisms on fine
eyes.